<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1855-01-31 frozen open river and bridges</title>
            <author>Henry David Thoreau</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-12-14</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>unknown</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document written by mharty</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application when="2016-05-22T17:30:16Z"
                         ident="convert_little_TEI_files.xslt"
                         version="0.1.1">
               <desc>
                  <label>pass 1:</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>indent</item>
                     <item>insert title</item>
                     <item>correct author</item>
                     <item>move time of OxGarage conversion</item>
                     <item>convert those “,” things to just comma</item>
                     <item>for MH text files, insert corresponding MH citation</item>
                  </list>
               </desc>
            </application>
            <application xml:id="docxtotei"
                         ident="TEI_fromDOCX"
                         version="2.15.0"
                         when="2016-05-20T22:49:22Z">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“I skated up as far as the boundary between Wayland and Sudbury just above Pelham’s Pond, to a point which a woman called about one and a half miles from Saxonville, about twelve miles, between 10 A.M. and one, quite leisurely. There I found the river open unexpectedly, as if there were a rapid there, and as I walked up it some three quarters of a mile, it was still open before me a half-mile further at least, or probably to the falls. Somewhat like this. All the open part, one and a half miles at least, was pretty closely hemmed in by highlands. I skated about twelve miles and walked three quarters of a mile further. It was, all the way that I skated, a chain of meadows, with the muskrat-houses still rising above the ice, commonly on the bank of the river, and marking it like smaller haycocks amid the large ones still left. I skated past three bridges above Sherman’s –or nine in all (?) –and walked to the fourth. The next, or fifth, would probably be that in middle of Saxonville. <hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi> Causeway bridges, Mill Village Bridge at Larned Brook, Pelham Pond Bridge, and that on road from Dudley Pond to Southboro and Marlboro.” </p>
         <p>"XVIII / 3 September 1854-12 May 1855 / NNPM MA 1302:24 / PE 9, p.156 vol. 8; Torrey JVII, p.#"</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
