<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1854-08-20 gibbous fish head</title>
            <author>Henry David Thoreau</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-11-29</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>unknown</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document written by mharty</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application when="2016-05-22T17:30:16Z"
                         ident="convert_little_TEI_files.xslt"
                         version="0.1.1">
               <desc>
                  <label>pass 1:</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>indent</item>
                     <item>insert title</item>
                     <item>correct author</item>
                     <item>move time of OxGarage conversion</item>
                     <item>convert those “,” things to just comma</item>
                     <item>for MH text files, insert corresponding MH citation</item>
                  </list>
               </desc>
            </application>
            <application xml:id="docxtotei"
                         ident="TEI_fromDOCX"
                         version="2.15.0"
                         when="2016-05-20T22:48:35Z">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“Off Dodge’s Brook saw a fish lying still on its side on the surface with its head downward slowly steering toward the shore with an undulating motion of the tail. Found it to be a large sucker which had ap. been struck by a king fisher? (or heron?) &amp; got away- (The mill is not agoing today Sunday). It had been seized near the tail which for 3 inches was completely flayed &amp; much torn –lacerated a part of the caudal fin being carried off. It had also received a severe thrust mid way its body –which had furrowed its side &amp; turned down a large strip of skin. It was breathing its last when I caught it. It was evidently too powerful for the bird which had struck it. It weighed 2 lbs &amp; 2 ounces &amp; was 19 ¼ inches long. Above it was a sort of blue black or slate color darkest on the head- with blotches of the same extending down its sides which were of a reddish golden passing into white beneath. There were a few small red spots on the sides just behind the gills. It had what I should call a gibbous head but no horns- a line of fine mucous pores above &amp; below eye- Eyes at least 1 ½ inches apart.”</p>
         <p>"XVII   /   13 February-3 September 1854   /   NNPM MA 1302:23   /   PE 8, p.285 vol.8; Torrey JVI &amp; JVII, p.#"</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
