<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1854-03-10 skunk</title>
            <author>Henry David Thoreau</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-10-27</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>unknown</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document written by mharty</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application when="2016-05-22T17:30:16Z"
                         ident="convert_little_TEI_files.xslt"
                         version="0.1.1">
               <desc>
                  <label>pass 1:</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>indent</item>
                     <item>insert title</item>
                     <item>correct author</item>
                     <item>move time of OxGarage conversion</item>
                     <item>convert those “,” things to just comma</item>
                     <item>for MH text files, insert corresponding MH citation</item>
                  </list>
               </desc>
            </application>
            <application xml:id="docxtotei"
                         ident="TEI_fromDOCX"
                         version="2.15.0"
                         when="2016-05-20T22:46:54Z">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“Saw a skunk in the Corner road- which I followed 60 rods or more. Out now about 4 pm- partly because it is a dark foul day- It is slender black (and white0 animal with its back remarkably arched- standing high behind- and carrying its head low- runs- even when undisturbed- with a singular teter or undulation- like the walking of a Chinese lady. Very slow- I hardly have to run to keep up with it. It has a long tail which it regularly erects when I come too near &amp; prepares to discharge its liquid. It is white at the end of the tail- &amp; the hind head- &amp; a line on the front of the face- the rest black- except the flesh colored nose (and I think feet). The back is more arched &amp; the fore 7 hind feet nearer together than in my sketch. It tried repeatedly to get into the wall- &amp; did not show much cunning. Finally it steered, apparently, for an old skunk or woodchuck hole under a wall 4 rods off- &amp; got into it- or under the wall at least- for it was stopped up- And there I view at leisure close to. It has a remarkably long narrow pointed head &amp; snout which enable it to make those deep narrow holes in the earth by which it probes for insects- Its eyes have an innocent child-like bluish black expression. It made a singular loud patting sound repeatedly on the frozen ground under the wall- undoubtedly with its fore feet- (I saw only the upper part of the animal0 which reminded me of what I have heard about stopping &amp; stamping in order to stop the skunk. Probably it has to do with its getting its food- patting the earth to get the insects or worms- Though why it did so then I know not.”</p>
         <p>"XV   /   9 March-18 August 1853   /   NNPM MA 1302:21   /   PE 6, p.36 vol.8; Torrey JV, p.#"</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
