<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1854-08-23 Gowing swamp</title>
            <author>Henry David Thoreau</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-12-03</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>unknown</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document written by mharty</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application when="2016-05-22T17:30:16Z"
                         ident="convert_little_TEI_files.xslt"
                         version="0.1.1">
               <desc>
                  <label>pass 1:</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>indent</item>
                     <item>insert title</item>
                     <item>correct author</item>
                     <item>move time of OxGarage conversion</item>
                     <item>convert those “,” things to just comma</item>
                     <item>for MH text files, insert corresponding MH citation</item>
                  </list>
               </desc>
            </application>
            <application xml:id="docxtotei"
                         ident="TEI_fromDOCX"
                         version="2.15.0"
                         when="2016-05-20T22:48:40Z">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“Pm to Gowing’s swamp &amp; Hawlock meadows, I improve the dry weather to examine the middle of G’s swamp. There is in the middle an open pool 20 or 30 feet in diameter nearly full of sphagnum &amp; green froth on the surface (frog-spittle) and what other plants I could not see on account of the danger in standing on the quaking ground. Then a dense border a rod or more wide of a peculiar rush (?) with clusters of seed vessels 3 together now going to seed a yel. green –forming an abrupt edge next the water this one dense bed of quaking sphagnum- in which I sink 18 inches in water upheld by its matted roots where I fear to break through- On this the spatulate sundew abounds. This is marked by the paths of muskrats.</p>
         <p>	Next comes half a dozen rods wide a dense bed of Andromeda Calyculata The A. polifolia mingled with it- the rusty cotton grass-cranberries the common &amp; also V. Oxycoccus-pitcher plants- sedge 7 a few young speuce &amp; larch here &amp; there – All on sphagnum –which forms little hillocks about the stems of the Andromeda.”</p>
         <p>"XVII   /   13 February-3 September 1854   /   NNPM MA 1302:23   /   PE 8, p.291 vol.8; Torrey JVI &amp; JVII, p.#"</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
