<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1855-01-25 partridge track</title>
            <author>Henry David Thoreau</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-12-07</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>unknown</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document written by mharty</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application when="2016-05-22T17:30:16Z"
                         ident="convert_little_TEI_files.xslt"
                         version="0.1.1">
               <desc>
                  <label>pass 1:</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>indent</item>
                     <item>insert title</item>
                     <item>correct author</item>
                     <item>move time of OxGarage conversion</item>
                     <item>convert those “,” things to just comma</item>
                     <item>for MH text files, insert corresponding MH citation</item>
                  </list>
               </desc>
            </application>
            <application xml:id="docxtotei"
                         ident="TEI_fromDOCX"
                         version="2.15.0"
                         when="2016-05-20T22:49:07Z">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“This morning was a perfect hunter’s morn, for it snowed about three quarters of an inch last evening, covering land and ice. Is not good skating a sign of snow? In the swamps, however, wher ethere was water oozed out over the ice, there is no snow, but frozen slosh to-day, i.e. a rotten, roughish, dull-white ice. It is a rare day for winter, clear and bright, yet warm. The warmth and stillness in the hollows about the Andromeda Ponds are charming. You dispense with gloves. I see mice-tracks in the fields and meadows like this: four together, rabbit-like, four or five inches apart and one and a quarter broad. Are they the same with the? I think so. I see rabbit-tracks, pretty large, maybe white ones, two feet apart. I suspect that in each case they are coming down the page. In partridge-tracks, the side toes are more spread than in crows; and I believe the hind one is not so long. Both trail the middle toe. The partidge-track looks like this: I see the tracks apparentyl of many hunters that hastened out this morning.“</p>
         <p>"XVIII / 3 September 1854-12 May 1855 / NNPM MA 1302:24 / PE 9, p.142 vol. 8; Torrey JVII, p.#"</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
