<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1856-01-01 leaves in ice</title>
            <author>Henry David Thoreau</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-11-06</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>unknown</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document written by Nick D'Amore</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application when="Z" ident="convert_little_TEI_files.xslt" version="0.0.1">
               <desc>
                  <label>pass 1:</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>indent</item>
                     <item>insert title</item>
                     <item>correct author</item>
                     <item>move time of OxGarage conversion</item>
                     <item>convert those “,” things to just comma</item>
                  </list>
               </desc>
            </application>
            <application xml:id="docxtotei"
                         ident="TEI_fromDOCX"
                         version="2.15.0"
                         when="2016-05-20T22:52:36Z">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“On the ice at Walden are very beautiful great leaf crystals in great profusion. The ice is frequently thickly connected with the rosettes, –a running together of them. They look like a loose web of small white feathers from a tuft of down, for their shafts are lost in a tuft of fine snow like the down about the shaft of a feather, as if a feather bed had been shaken over the ice. They are, on a close examination, surprisingly perfect leaves, like ferns, only very broad for their length and commonly more on one side the midrib than the other. They are from an inch to an inch and a half long and three quarters wide, and slanted, where I look, from the southwest. They have, first “&lt;’ a very distinct midrib, though so thin that they cannot be taken up; then, distinct ribs branching from this, commonly opposite, and minute ribs springing again from these last, as in many ferns, the last running to each crenation in the boarder. How much further they are subdivided, the naked eye cannot discern. They are so thin and fragile that they melt under your breath while looking closely at them.”</p>
         <p>PE 10, pg. 77 / 13 May 1855-3 January 1856 / NNPM MA 1302:25 / T vol. # XIX / PDF # XIV / JVII &amp; JVIII</p>
         <p>Location: Walden Pond</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
