<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1856-07-29 swallows nest</title>
            <author>Henry David Thoreau</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2015-11-06</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>unknown</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document written by Nick D'Amore</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application when="2016-05-21T00:50:04Z"
                         ident="convert_little_TEI_files.xslt"
                         version="0.0.1">
               <desc>
                  <label>pass 1:</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>indent</item>
                     <item>insert title</item>
                     <item>correct author</item>
                     <item>move time of OxGarage conversion</item>
                     <item>convert those “,” things to just comma</item>
                  </list>
               </desc>
            </application>
            <application xml:id="docxtotei"
                         ident="TEI_fromDOCX"
                         version="2.15.0"
                         when="2016-05-20T22:54:15Z">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>“Pratt gave me a chimney swallow’s nest, which he says fell down Wesson’s chimney with young in it two or three days ago. As it comes to me, it is in the form of the segment of the circumference of a sphere whose diameter is three and a half inches, the segment being two plus wide, one side, of course, longer than the other. It bears a little soot on the inner side. It may have been placed against a slanting part of the chimney, or perhaps some of the outer edge is broken off. It is composed wholly of stout twigs, one to two inches long, one sixteenth to one eighth inch diameter, held quasi cob-fashion so as to form a sort of basketwork one third to one half inch thick, without any lining, at least in this, but very open to the air. These twigs, which are quite knubby, seem to be of the apple, elm, and the link, and are firmly fastened together by a very conspicucous whitish semi-transparent glue, which is laid on pretty copiously, sometimes extending continuously one inch.”</p>
         <p>PE 11, pg. 432-433 / 23 April-6 September 1856 / NNPM MA 1302:27 / T vol. # XXI / PDF # XIV / JVIII &amp; JIX</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
