<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author>Nick D'Amore</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2015-11-29</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2016-05-20T22:54:58Z</date><name>Nick D'Amore</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>“This morning (the 15<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>) “,” it having rained in the night “,” and thinking the fire would be mostly out “,” I made haste to the ruins of the Lee house to read that inscription. By laying down boards on the bricks and cinders “,” which were quite too hot to tread on and covered a smothered fire “,” I was able to reach the chimney. The inscription was on the east side of the east chimney (which had fallen) “,” at the bottom “,” in a cupboard on the west side of the late parlor “,” which was on a level with the ground on the east and with the cellar on the extreme west and the cellar kitchen on the north. There was a narrow lower (milk) cellar south and southeast of it “,” and an equally lower and narrower cellar east of it “,” under the parlor. This side of the chimney was perhaps fifteen feet from the east side of the house and as far from the north side. The inscription was in a slight recess in the chimney three feet four inches wide and a little more in height up and down “,” as far as I could see into the pile of bricks thus: --[image] It appeared to have been made by the finger or a stick in the mortar when fresh “,” which had been spread an inch to an inch and a quarter thick over the bricks “,” and “,” where it was too dry and hard “,” to have been pecked with the point of a trowel. The first three words and the ‘16’ where perfectly plain “,” the ‘5’ was tolerably plain “,” though some took it for a three “,” but I could <hi rend="italic">fee</hi> it yet more distinctly. The mortar was partly knocked off the rest “,” apparently by this fire “,” but the top of some capital letter like a ‘C,’ and the letters ‘netty’ were about as plain as represented “,” and the rest looked like ‘Henry’ (Woodhouse?) or “l(t?)kinry’ the ‘y’ at end being crowded  for want of room next the side. These last two words <hi rend="italic">quite</hi> uncertain. The surface of this recess was slightly swelling or bulging “,” like the outside of an over “,” and above it the chimney was sloped and rounded off to the narrower shaft of it. The letters were from two and one half to three inches long and one eighth to one half in deep.”</p><p>PE 11, pg. 258-259 / 7 September 1856-1 April 1857/ NNPM MA 1302:28 / T vol. # XXII / PDF # XV / JIX </p></body></text></TEI>