<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author>Nick D'Amore</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2015-11-29</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2016-05-20T22:55:00Z</date><name>Nick D'Amore</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>“By Thrush Alley “,” where they have been cutting more wood this winter “,” I see one of those beetles made of an oak excrescence “,” such as I have heard of “,” left by the chopper. The whole is a little over four feet long. The head nine or ten inches and the handle about three and a half feet “,” but all one pice. It was apparently of a young tree “,” or perhaps a limb “,” about four inches in diameter with a regular excrescence about it still “,” eight or nine inches in diameter. This head had been smothered or trimmed and made more regular by the axe “,” cut off rather square at the end “,” and the lower part cut down to a handle of convenient size. And thus the chopper had made in a few moments in the woods a really efficient implement “,” with his axe only “,” out of some of the very wood he wished to split. A natural beetle. There was no danger that the handle would come off or the head crack. It needed no ringing. And thus he saved the head of his axe. We are singularly pleased and contened when a mere excrescence is thus converted into a convenient implement. Who was it “,” what satyr “,” that invented this rustic beetle? It was shaped: [image] And indispensable piece of woodcraft.”</p><p>PE 11, pg. 295/ 7 September 1856-1 April 1857/ NNPM MA 1302:28 / T vol. # XXII / PDF # XV / JIX </p></body></text></TEI>