<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author>Nick D'Amore</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2016-02-18</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2016-05-20T22:56:01Z</date><name>Nick D'Amore</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>“Looking north from Hubbard’s Bridge about 4 pm “,” the wing being southeasterly “,”I am struck by the varied lights of the river. The wind “,” which is a considerable breeze “,” strikes the water by a very irregular serrated edge about mid-channel “,” and then abruptly leaves it on a distinct and regular meandering line “,” about eight feet from the outer edge of the pads on the west side. The rippled portion of the river is blue “,” the rest smooth “,” silvery. Thus to my eye the river is divided into five portions “,” –first the weedy and padded borders “,” then a smooth “,” silvery stripe “,” eight or ten feet wide “,” and next the blue rippled portion “,” succeeded by the broader silver “,” and the pads of the eastern side. How many aspects the river wears “,” depending on the height of the water “,” the season of the year and state of vegetation “,” the wind “,” the position of the sun and condition of the heavens “,” etc. “,” etc.! Apparently such is the angle at which the wind strikes the river from over the bushes that it falls about mid-channel “,” and then it is either obliged to leave it at a nearly similar angle on account of the opposite shore and bushes “,” or perchance “,” the smoothing influence of the pads is felt to some distance beyond their edges. The line which separates the smooth from the rippled portion is as distinct and continuous as that which marks the edge of the pads. I think that there is more oily matter floating on the stiller sides of the rive “,” and this too may have something to do with the above phenomenon. Then there is the watered appearance of the surface in a shower.”</p><p>PE 14, pg. 84-85 / 9 July 1858-9 November 1858 / NNPM MA 1302:33 / T vol. # XXVII / PDF # XVII / JXI</p></body></text></TEI>