<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title/><author>Nick D'Amore</author></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition><date>2016-02-08</date></edition></editionStmt><publicationStmt><p>unknown</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Converted from a Word document</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><appInfo><application xml:id="docxtotei" ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0"><label>DOCX to TEI</label></application></appInfo></encodingDesc><revisionDesc><listChange><change><date>2016-05-20T22:55:49Z</date><name>Nick D'Amore</name></change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><p>“In one or two places on this side of the mountain “,” which “,” as I have said “,” terminated in an abrupt precipice “,” I saw bogs or meadows four or six rods wide or more “,” but with only grass and moss and eriophorum “,” without bushes “,” in them “,” close to the edge of the mountain or precipice “,” where “,” if you stood between the meadow and the summit “,” looking east “,” there would appear to be a notch in the rim of the cup or saucer on the east and the meadow ready to spill over and run down the mountain on that side; but when you stood on this notched edge “,” the descent was seen to be much less precipitous than you had expected. Such spongy mountain bogs “,” however “,” are evidently the sources of rivers. Lakes of the clouds when they are clear water. Between this and the northeast spur or ridge was the largest swamp or bog that I saw “,” consisting “,” perhaps “,” of between one and two acres “,” as I remember. It was a grassy and mossy bog without large bushes “,” in which you sank a foot “” with a great many fallen trees in it “,” showing their bleached upper side here and there but almost completely buried in the moss. This must once have been a dense swamp “,” full of pretty large trees. The trees buried in the moss were much larger than any now standing at this height. The outlet of this “,” it it had any “,” must have been northwesterly. This was a wild place enough.”</p><p>PE 13, pg. 472-472 / 25 November 1857-4 June 1858/ NNPM MA 1302:31 / T vol. # XXV / PDF # XVI / JX</p></body></text></TEI>